Welcome to On the Brink. My name is Sean Judge. Today on the show, I sat down with Santi Alvarado,
CEO and co-founder of XFX. Earlier this week, we announced Castle Island invested in XFX's seed
round of financing alongside Han Ventures, Oak HCFT, Maya Capital, Coinbase, Paxos, and others.
Please enjoy today's conversation with Santi Alvarado.
Matt Walsh and Nick Carter are partners at Castle Island Ventures. All of these expressed by them
or the guests on this podcast are solely their opinions and do not reflect the opinions of
Castle Island Ventures. Guests and hosts may maintain positions in the assets discussed in
this podcast. You should not treat any opinion expressed by anyone on this podcast as a specific
inducement to make a particular investment or follow a particular strategy, but only as an
expression of their personal opinion. This podcast is for informational purposes only.
The federal government is stepping in to stabilize Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac,
the two mortgage giants that have been threatened by the housing crisis.
The Bank of England has pumped 75 billion pounds more into Britain's ailing economy
with a new round of quantitative easing. You print a couple trillion dollars and all
of a sudden people start to worry. So out of this worry, we have something called the Bitcoin.
Welcome to On the Brink. My name is Sean Judge. Today I'm sitting down with Santi Alvarado,
CEO and co-founder of XFX. Santi, thanks for joining me.
Thank you for having me, Sean. Pleasure to be here.
I guess just to start, it would be great if you could share your personal background and
how you arrived at working in crypto. I'm actually Peruvian, although I haven't
lived in Peru for over a decade. And in what I call my past life, I did something very different
to what I'm doing now. I'm a civil engineer and I worked on infrastructure development across Latin
America, mostly in energy and transportation, then got an MBA degree at Harvard Business School.
And after that is when my fintech career started, I had the opportunity to launch and scale a
digital bank called Tempo in Chile. Interestingly, that's the first time I actually bought Bitcoin.
It was out of frustration with my bank trying to send money back home to Peru,
where I got stuck in what I call swift limbo, right? Where you don't know where the money's
going to arrive, the fees that you're going to pay. Ultimately, the money ended up arriving
seven days later. And they usually charged me around $150, which I thought was unacceptable.
So I opened an account at a Chilean exchange, an account at a Peruvian exchange, and I started
buying Bitcoin with Chilean pesos and selling it for Peruvian soles. And it took me 15 minutes
and a fraction of a glass. I thought there was something very powerful there. Although, of course,
the user experience was still a bit tricky. So I decided to create a cross-border payments business
leveraging blockchain. And Bitcoin specifically, stablecoins were not a thing back then.
And a friend of mine from business school, who was the CFO at Bitsol, told me, why don't you join
Bitsol and do this business with us? So about five years ago, I joined Bitsol to launch what was then
called the cross-border payments business unit, which ended up becoming Bitsol Business, which is
Bitsol's B2B business unit. It's amazing. I mean, I give Bitsol a lot of credit for thinking about
that five years ago. I mean, it's obviously very in vogue today, but five years ago, it was less
obvious that this would be a huge opportunity. So you had your experience there. XFX, you just
raised for earlier this week, and we were proud to be investors in that round. What is the high
level overview of XFX? And who did you start this with? In a nutshell, the way that I would describe
XFX is a financial infrastructure for international settlement. And what we provide is,
we give access to institutions to wholesale FX liquidity and real-time settlement,
saving in capital costs by not having to pre-fund origin or destination accounts.
I started this business with my two co-founders called Jason Loesch and Alberto, we call him Beto,
Sanchez Tello, and we all met at Bitsol. So Jason used to lead the engineering team at Bitsol,
and Beto led the markets team, which is basically a team that's in charge of the liquidity in the
exchange for both retail and institutional business units. Zooming out a little bit,
for those listeners that are maybe less familiar with the FX market or cross-border payments
market, I think it's pretty jarring when you dig into the numbers. Can you share just how big of
a market this is and maybe how it operates today? So the FX market is the largest financial market
in the world in terms of TPB. It moves $7.5 trillion a day. And if you think about it,
it makes sense because ultimately, most of financial services actually have to go through
an FX transaction. If you're thinking about international trade, trading commodities,
if you're thinking about global equity or debt, this usually have an FX transaction embedded in
it. It's an absolutely massive market, but it has its complexities that I'm happy to talk about.
So let's start with a settlement piece. Most people have heard about Swift, and Swift really
is only a messaging system between banks. But the actual money movement happens across
correspondent banks, meaning that each of these banks in that payment chain need to have what
are called Nostro and Vostro accounts at each other in the corresponding currency for
different types of currency pairs. There are $4 trillion of tied up capital in this Nostro-Vostro
account. So if you actually think about the cost breakdown of the average cross-border payments
transaction, around 60% is composed of the cost of capital of that tied up capital and the FX
price. So that's on the settlement side, right? And then on the trading side, there are also
complexities, right? Usually the market, and this is very strange for such a large market,
is very opaque. If you ask anyone that's engaged regularly with FX providers, they always feel
like they're being taken advantage of. There's very little transparency on whether you're actually
getting a competitive price. And also behind the scenes, there are settlement and cost of capital
problems. For instance, if you want to trade at the spot rate in the Mexican FX market,
the funds settle P plus 2. That also means quite a bit of working capital tied up in the system.
And it's no wonder that if you want to trade from Monday to Wednesday, you can get a better rate
that if you want to trade Thursday and Friday, because if you trade Thursday, the funds will
settle on Monday. Therefore there's an additional cost of capital due to the weekend. Incredible
that that's the way the market exists today in 2025. That's largely been unchanged literally
since the late seventies. And then I guess that's where stable coins come in. So most of our listeners
will be familiar with stable coins, but maybe in your words, why do you see stable coins as
improving upon the existing ways in which money moves cross border? A lot of that tied up capital.
The most exciting thing for me about stable coins is that for the first time, we have
a standard that the ecosystem can agree upon and actually build according to that standard for
cross border payments. Not only that, but unlike Swift, which is only the messaging system,
stable coins are both things. They're the messaging system and the movement of value.
A few relevant components that are missing for the asset class, and by asset class I mean stable
coins, to truly deliver its intended value proposition, which is real-time cross-border
settlement without pre-funding requirements so that it can actually out-compete the
trade-fine mechanisms today. That's why we're actually building XFX because we think we can
actually build that base layer infrastructure to make sure that that value proposition happens.
It makes a lot of sense. Now, were there experiences that you've had just in your journey
working in fintech and eventually working in crypto where you felt like this just had to exist?
It just was very obvious. Maybe just on that, if you could explain in a little bit more detail
who the key players are involved in a cross-border stable coin transaction and where things were
starting to break and what you guys are building to help facilitate that.
Let's talk about one use case where this is very visible and where the system is broken,
which are remittances and e-commerce. On the remittance side, you have money transmitters.
Those money transmitters promise their end users same-day settlement, but the money does not arrive
same day, meaning that there's a gap that they need to pre-fund in order for them to actually
meet their payments as late. The same is true for a PSP that offers same-day settlement for
a foreign merchant. So the foreign merchant hires the PSP to manage all the collections domestically
and then they need to settle with them whichever jurisdictions are incorporated in or have their
bank accounts at. And the same working capital problem happens. In fact, it's actually even worse
because they need to process the domestic card network, which usually settles in two days,
and then you have the swift problem. Depending on the origin destination, they could be pre-funding
up to, let's say, five days of TPB to meet their SLAs with their customers. And that actually makes
no sense, right? Especially if you think about all of the real-time payment networks that are
appearing in different markets like PICS in Brazil, Spain, Mexico, FedNow in the US. Why does the
cross-border payments space still need to happen in batch? That's to a large degree the problem
that stable coins can get to solve. That can happen from a programmatic standpoint,
but the liquidity is still not there. So the problem that we're solving at XFX is making sure
that regardless of the amount that you want to trade, first that you can do it programmatically
and that you can access the most competitive liquidity consistently at all times for that
asset plus. Therefore, really trying to make the cross-border payments a value chain real-time on
a per-transaction basis instead of on a batch basis. As we've talked about a bunch, we're
investors in Felix Pago. And from an end user's perspective, the digital remitters that emerged
15 years ago are able to kind of do, and I'm using quotation marks, instant payments because
for the user, it feels that way. But those digital remitters are forced to kind of park capital all
over the world to facilitate that. Whereas with stable coins, there's the opportunity to kind of
actually do it instant with less capital tied up. The only issue there is, is there liquidity on
the other end, which is kind of where you guys come into play? And not only that, I would have
an additional problem that goes beyond the parked capital. It's that all of the rebalancing has to
happen in batch and it usually happens in an analog manner, literally via phone call or a WhatsApp
channel with your relationship manager at a bank or FX provider. Can you share, I guess,
just on the product side, what does the product look like today for businesses looking to move
money and then maybe what it looks like for the FX market maker side? There are three main product
pillars in our product offering. The first is the settlement layer, where we actually give
access to the domestic banking rails for the currency pairs that we want to support,
as well as the stablecoin networks that we want to support. The second is the trade execution
capabilities, which is an RFQ system plus the trade execution capabilities,
which always happen in real time. And with full transparency, you'll always be able to audit
the trade breakdown with the system. And third are the post-trade settlement capabilities,
which in essence give payments institutions the ability to even improve their working capital
further, where they can actually execute a trade with us and then settle T plus one, T plus two,
or T plus three. As you guys are talking to folks in the market, are there core aspects of the
settlement platform that makes XFX stand out for institutional clients? Is it that post-trade
settlement component? So I'd say that the first thing is the consistency in price and depth for
all the currency pairs that we support. It makes no sense to integrate to a platform
that cannot deliver on that consistency and visibility for the trade. And unfortunately,
that's not the case for stablecoins, particularly in less liquid markets like Latin markets.
Second is the settlement speed. All the settlement happens in real time,
and that equates to no pre-funding, no tied up capital. The third thing is the transparency.
So if we actually agree on commercial terms, you'll always be able to audit, regardless of
the mechanism and the trade size, that that is the spread that you are actually getting,
which is, let's say, Bloomberg market rate plus X basis points. And the third thing is the
programmability to make sure that you have the flexibility to operate either via Web UI and OTC,
but most importantly, you can actually automate this whole operation via a great set of APIs.
To get going, obviously you'll have plans to expand, but here initially,
what pairs do you plan to support? We're starting with three currency pairs,
which are USDFIA against MXN, USDC against MXN, and USDT against MXN. But our plan is to remain
always agnostic to the stablecoin that we want to route volume through. We'll always follow the
optimal path for settlement speed and liquidity. In terms of roadmap, we want to move to the rest
of Spanish-speaking Latam. We believe that the places where this technology is really 10X better
than the existing trade fair alternatives is in the less liquid, more exotic markets.
So we'll start there, but the idea is to build a global business.
Well, I think with this infrastructure, which will enable even more interesting business and
consumer applications to get built on top of you guys, now that it's making it just that much more
efficient. Well, this has been awesome, Santi. Where can people learn more about XFX and you?
You can go to our website, which is xfx.io, or follow us on X. The handle is at officialxfx.
Well, congrats again on the seat around. Super pumped to be partnered with you
and the team. And thanks so much for joining today.
Thank you, Sean. It's been a pleasure.
Thanks for listening to another episode of On the Brink with Castle Island. To find out
more about Castle Island, visit castleisland.vc. To listen to all of our podcast episodes,
please go to onthebrink-podcast.com or just click on the tab in our website. Thanks for listening.